Today's דף daf is קכ"ז, Kuf Chaf Zayin, 127. We start at
the very bottom of קכ"ו עמוד ב'. Kuf Chaf Vav Amud Bet.
You are, we are away from the whole issues about, well not
really away, but moved a little bit beyond some of the discussions
about the skin and the bone being a שומר. shomer. And for
those who weren't here the last two days, there was a major
discussion about טומאת מת tumas meis and how the טומאה tuma of
pieces of a dead, of a corpse, zoom up into the air
and whether it's like touching or tenting over it. Now we turn
to a new משנה. mishna. The new משנה mishna discussed the issue
of שרצים, sheratzim, rodents, the, there are eight שרצים sheratzim in the
תורה, Torah, specific types of rodents and, excuse me, what's that, what
are those things called, lizards, yeah, but what's the term for them?
Reptiles, thank you.
Little pop quiz for the class.
No, no, no, rodents and reptiles that are
טמא. tamei. Anyway, and spoke about a similar idea that if you
touch the egg of the reptiles, because you don't have access to
this growing fetus inside, you're טהור, tahor, but if there's a hole
in it, you're טמא. tamei. And then we had a bizarre and
fascinating case of a rat, an עכבר, achbar, that the rabbis understood
grew from the ground, did not grow through, grew through some type
of spontaneous generation, and that at a certain stage of its development
could be half ground and half rat as it was developing. And
the question was, what is the status of that half ground part
of it, is it טמא tamei like the rat itself or not?
So the rat was generating out of the...
No, no, they, you know, look, they cannot be held to a
science beyond their days. I mean, spontaneous generation was only disproven in
when, 17th century or something? Yeah, so, you know, it was a,
it was a very common belief and that was, so they dealt
with that case. Let's take a look now at the גמרא Gemara
on תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the last narrow line of קכ"ו עמוד
ב', Kuf Chaf Vav Amud Bet, middle of the line. Our rabbis
taught, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, מתוך שנאמר עכבר, mitoch shene'emar achbar, the
תורה Torah says עכבר, achbar, that one of the eight שרצים sheratzim
that are טמא tamei when they die, which is normally translated as
a rat, maybe a mouse, שומע אני אפילו עכבר שבים, shome'a ani
afilu achbar shebayam,
maybe even this sea עכבר, achbar, there was a certain animal that
they called the sea עכבר, achbar, the sea rat, that is called
an
עכבר. achbar. I mean, we have something we call a sea horse,
so they called something a sea rat. So maybe that's included in
these שרצים. sheratzim. ודין הוא, vedin hu, and it makes sense, we
could learn it from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, or at least
an analogy. טימא בחולדה וטימא בעכבר, tima bechulda vetima be'achbar, it says
a חולדה chulda is טמא tamei and an עכבר achbar is טמא.
tamei. מה חולדה מן הגדל על הארץ אף עכבר מן הגדל על
הארץ. ma chulda min hagadel al ha'aretz af achbar min hagadel al
ha'aretz.
So by analogy, we just say the same way חולדה chulda is
only a land animal, the עכבר achbar also refers only to the
land animal and not the sea animal that's called an עכבר. achbar.
או כלך לדרך זו, o kalech laderech zu, go this way. טימא
בחולדה וטימא בעכבר, tima bechulda vetima be'achbar, same analogy. It says that
a חולדה chulda weasel is טמא tamei and an עכבר achbar is
טמא. tamei. מה חולדה כל ששמו חולדה, ma chulda kol sheshmo chulda,
the term חולדה chulda applies to any animal whose name is a
חולדה. chulda. חולדה, chulda, there is not a sea version of it.
So you could, by making the analogy one way, you could say
only a land animal. Making the analogy another way, you could say
anything that's called by that term. So the same way a חולדה,
chulda, it's all animals called חולדה, chulda, אף עכבר כל ששמו עכבר,
af achbar kol sheshmo achbar, by עכבר achbar we'll say anything called
an עכבר, achbar, including the עכבר שבים, achbar shebayam, אפילו עכבר שבים,
afilu achbar shebayam,
even the sea עכבר, achbar, ששמו עכבר. sheshmo achbar. תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar, so the verse teaches, על הארץ. al ha'aretz. It says this
is for you the things that are טמא, tamei, השרץ השורץ על
הארץ, hasheretz hashoretz al ha'aretz, which creeps on the ground. So only
land animals, not sea animals. אי על הארץ יכול על הארץ יטמא
ירד לים לא יטמא. i al ha'aretz yachol al ha'aretz yitamei yarad
layam lo yitamei. Maybe we should read the word on the ground
differently. Not a land animal, a type of animal that is, you
know, stays, that is fundamentally lives on the land, but while it's
on the land. So maybe if the normal rat drowns in the
sea and you touch it there, maybe you're not טמא. tamei. Maybe
it's only טמא tamei when it's on the ground. Meaning it's about
the circumstances, the geography, the location of it, not the type of
animal it is. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so top of קכ"ז עמוד
א', Kuf Chaf Zayin Amud Aleph, so the verse teaches, השורץ, hashoretz,
that creeps, מכל מקום ששורץ, mikol makom sheshoretz, wherever it will creep.
So therefore that's coming to include even if it happens to be
in the sea. And the word land refers to not where it
is, but what type of animal it is, only land animals. Yes.
Like a great purification? It was a bizarre, no,
no,
we would never say that. It's just a, it's just a, there's
no real logic to it. It's just a, it's just saying like,
you know, maybe it's an arbitrary rule of the verse. Maybe if
the verse says this is טמא tamei on the land, it doesn't
refer to the type of animal, it terms, it refers to the
location. But I don't think the גמרא Gemara is suggesting the logic
that the sea is purified because the classic example in the גמרא
Gemara about like, you know,
it's
the great... That's the שרץ sheretz that causes טומאה, tumah, so you're
going through this process of purification but you're holding on to the
sin. So if you take something טמא tamei into a מקוה mikvah
it remains I mean the source of טומאה tumah remains it's only
something that has like contracted טומאה tumah or for somebody who's finishing
the purification process, but you can't take a corpse or a dead
rodent into a מקוה mikvah and make it טהור. tahor. This seems
to be just a question of like maybe an arbitrary sort of
dictum of the verse. And maybe that's what על הארץ al ha'aretz
means and then of course rejects. על הארץ al ha'aretz is referred
to the type of rodent, not to its location.
Okay, so או אינו אלא השרץ כל המשריץ יטמא שאין משריץ לא
יטמא, o eino ela hasheretz kol hamashritz yitmei she'ein mashritz lo yitmei,
maybe שרץ sheretz means anything that is משריץ, mashritz, which here does
not mean creep and crawl but it means procreate, like the verse
says by בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael in שמות, Shemot, פרו וישרצו וירבו
ויעצמו במאוד מאוד. paru vayishretzu vayirbu vaya'atzmu bim'od me'od. They were fruitful
and they sort of, you know, multiplied, but וישרצו vayishretzu means, you
know, almost like, you know, they like insects multiplied. It's the metaphor,
but וישרצו vayishretzu does not necessarily mean creep, it could also mean
to procreate. So maybe that's what the verse is coming to say,
it has to procreate. הוציא עכבר שחציו בשר וחציו אדמה שאין פרה
ורבה. hotzi achbar she'chetzyo basar ve'chetzyo adamah she'ein pareh ve'ravah. And maybe
I'll exclude the case in the משנה, Mishnah, the rat that is
half, you know, ground and half meat, meaning that it's growing from
the ground, that it's not does not procreate. Right? Which again they
understood that this was spontaneous generation. ודמי? u'demi? And that makes sense.
תני בחולדה ותני בעכבר, tanei be'chuldah ve'tanei be'achbar, meaning I will make
an analogy to make this to make to make this argument the
opposite way, to make the argument that this type of a rat
that doesn't procreate is טמא. tamei. Why? Because it says that a
חולדה chuldah is טמא tamei and it says the rat is טמא.
tamei. So therefore, what should I say? מה חולדה כל ששמה חולדה
אף עכבר כל ששמו עכבר. mah chuldah kol she'shemah chuldah af achbar
kol she'shemo achbar. The same way by a חולדה, chuldah, let's say
a weasel, anything that's called a חולדה, chuldah, so אף עכבר כל
ששמו עכבר, af achbar kol she'shemo achbar, so that any rat would
include anything that's called a rat. אביא עכבר שחציו בשר וחציו אדמה.
avia achbar she'chetzyo basar ve'chetzyo adamah. So on the one hand, so
now we're saying we're for a while we were discussing the qualifications
of the sea עכבר, achbar, and there we were arguing to exclude
it because of the word ארץ. aretz. How about the analogy to
חולדה? chuldah? You could go either way. You could say חולדה chuldah
on the one hand is is is argues that any is a
land animal, so only land animals. On the other hand, you could
say חולדה chuldah means anything included in that term. Now we're making
the question about this animal that we that we believe grows through
spontaneous generation. So on the one hand you could make the argument:
anything that's called an עכבר, achbar, whether it naturally procreates or does
not, that's one argument to include it. או כלך לדרך זו, o
kalech lederech zu, or make the opposite argument. מה חולדה פרה ורבה,
mah chuldah pareh ve'ravah, the analogy to the חולדה chuldah is not
anything called by that name, but the same way חולדה chuldah is
procreates naturally, אף עכבר פרה ורבה, af achbar pareh ve'ravah, maybe only
a rat that procreates as opposed to this rat which is spontaneously
grows. So how do you know whether this rat that was believed
to be spontaneous generation should be included or not? On the one
hand it's like a it's included in the term עכבר, achbar, on
the other hand it's not similar to a חולדה chuldah which procreates.
So the גמרא Gemara says תלמוד לומר השרץ. talmud lomar hasheretz. It
says among the שרץ, sheretz, which is understood to again mean here...
that the ב bet somehow again it's not always clear to me
how what extra letter or aspect of the verse the גמרא Gemara
is learning to be inclusive, but somehow it's saying the extra בשרץ
basheretz is coming to tell me anything that's called a שרץ, sheretz,
even this thing that procreates at the end of the does not
procreate. At the end of the day, somehow through an extra letter
or an extra hint in the verse we include the idea of
even this rat that does not procreate. But what we exclude is
something that is a sea animal and not a land animal, because
it's השרץ על הארץ, hasheretz al ha'aretz, which we understand to mean
what type of animal it is, not where it happens to be.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say here, why not you've
included one and excluded the other? You've included the non-procreating rat, you
did not you excluded the sea rat. So why not reverse it,
and what tells you which one to include, which one to exclude?
Yes.
If an animal is created by spontaneous generation, that does not automatically
mean that it would not reproduce, just as there are animals that
are created through ordinary means that actually can't reproduce.
That's the reverse. That's it's created through it's through procreation and doesn't
reproduce. Here we're suggest here the גמרא Gemara understands that you're trying
to say it was not created through procreation but can reproduce.
Yeah, is there any reason why it couldn't?
It's true, but I don't know obviously
the גמרא Gemara is assuming that, obviously believes
that this animal by very definition only, you know, only was created
through spontaneous generation. All right, anyway, the nice thing is is that
it's not actually learning from a verse that it's like, you know,
it's meaning at the
end of the at the end of the day it's not being
well, what am I trying to say?
Even though it's got the science, it doesn't lead to any sort
of contrary claims, you know? I mean, they believed that this was
where the animal came from. They said it was טמא, tamei, even
if we realize that it's not created through spontaneous generation, they're still
saying that this rat is טמא. tamei. So it doesn't sort of
lead to any, you know, even though the science was wrong, it
doesn't actually lead to any sort of problematic conclusions. It's more challenging
when the wrong science leads to problematic conclusions, like the גמרא Gemara
that believe in the category of spontaneous generation that you could kill
lice on שבת Shabbos because they're not really, you know, they don't
procreate, and the only thing that you can't kill is types
of life that comes through procreation. So there there's a problem where
their incorrect science led to actually problematic conclusions.
I don't know of any פוסק posek nowadays that would actually say
it's מותר mutar to kill lice, you know? It becomes a question,
that becomes a larger issue of to what degree does הלכה halacha
change once we realize that the science is different. We talked about
that a lot earlier in the year. Yeah. So does הלכה halacha
change? It's a case-by-case question, you know, about
very often the, I mean, different פוסקים poskim have different approaches to
that. רב משה Rav Moshe writes in one תשובה teshuva that in
principle any הלכה halacha can be reassessed based on the new understanding
of science with one exception of טרפה, trefa, because טרפה trefa has
like this very well-defined, you know, list like הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'Moshe miSinai concept to it. But yeah, there's a general question amongst
פוסקים poskim about how much if we, some פוסקים poskim who really
resist the idea of opening the הלכה halacha to that, you know,
possibility, potential of so much change will try to argue that the
science was not really the basis for the position, that the science
was really like an after-the-fact, you know, sort of explanation, but the
position they knew through tradition to sort of decouple the two. But
that is a, yeah, that's definitely a very large question. Yeah.
So at least based on where we are with our understanding of
גמרא Gemara right now, they are not distinguishing between the spontaneously
generated rat
versus with the lice they are. That's what I said, that this
גמרא Gemara at least the conclusion is
non-problematic because, you know, even at the end of the day, they're
giving it the same status of something that does, you know, that
normally procreates. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
ליה ההוא מדרבנן לרבא. Amar lei hahu midirabbanan l'Rava. So one of
the rabbis says to רבא. Rava. Usually ההוא מדרבנן hahu midirabbanan means
like one of the rabbinic students says to רבא. Rava. אימא בשרץ
לרבות עכבר שחציו בשר וחציו אדמה. Eima basheretz lerabot achbar shechetzyo basar
vechetzyo adamah. Let's read it this way: בשרץ basheretz includes, like you
said, an animal that half ground, half flesh, meaning spontaneously generated.
השרץ כל שהוא שרץ ואפילו עכבר שבים. Hasheretz kol shehu sheretz va'afilu
achbar shebayam. What it says השרץ, hasheretz, it means
wherever, you know, any animal that creeps and crawls, even a sea
rat. And
והאי דמשום על הארץ vehai d'mishum al ha'aretz and the phrase on
the land, על הארץ יטמא ירד לים לא יטמא. al ha'aretz yitma
yarad layam lo yitma. Maybe only when it's on the ground, not
when it's in the sea. Meaning we have three issues we're dealing
with: sea rats versus land rats, where is the animal, on the
land and on the sea, and this case of non-spontaneously generated. So
he says, how do you know to split the verses the way
you did and to say, well, include non-spontaneously generated,
exclude sea rats, and include no matter where they are? Why don't
I agree with you that we'll include the non-spontaneously generated, but we'll
reverse the other two? We'll say even a sea rat is טמא
tamei and the phrase על הארץ al ha'aretz says it's only when
it's on the land, not when it's in the sea. So maybe
we'll reverse those two positions. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said back to him, מאחר דשויתיה לים מקום טומאה, me'achar deshaviteih layam
mekom tumah, once you've agreed that the ocean is a place where
טומאה tumah can exist, if you are including sea rats, so מה
לי הכא מה לי הכא, ma li hacha ma li hacha, why
would I care whether it's in the sea or on the land?
Meaning if I'm saying it's a type of a species, land rats
yes, sea rats no, then I could also say it doesn't matter
where the species is, whether you find the land rat in the
sea or you find it on the land. But if you're saying
a sea rat in the sea, excuse me, if you're saying a
sea rat is טמא, tamei, why should a sea rat be טמא
tamei only if it happens to be on the land? Once even
in the sea some creatures of the sea can be a source
of טומאה, tumah, why should it be limited to when they happen
to be on the land? That doesn't make any sense. והאי
על הארץ, Vehai al ha'aretz, okay, so that's how we know basically
the rulings of our משנה. Mishna. Only land rats, doesn't matter where
you find them, but includes these spontaneously generated rats. Now the גמרא
Gemara says והאי על הארץ מיבעי ליה להוציא ספק טומאה צפה. vehai
al ha'aretz miba'ei lei lehotzi safek tumah tzafa. Don't we need that
phrase על הארץ al ha'aretz to exclude a doubt of טומאה tumah
that is floating? And here, by the way, you do have this
place where being in the sea makes a difference, believe it or
not. דאמר רב יצחק בר אבדימי, De'amar Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, על
הארץ, al ha'aretz, that creeps on the ground, להוציא ספק טומאה צפה.
lehotzi safek tumah tzafa. If you have a doubt, doubtful טומאה tumah
and it's floating in the ocean, it is טהור. tahor. Now there's
a lot of very funny, relatively arbitrary laws by טומאה tumah with
doubts. One of them is that if it's a doubt that's in...
In a public domain, we assume that it's טהור, tahor, like you
touch something and you don't know if you touched a טומאה tumah
or not, or this thing was טמא tamei or not or whatever.
If it's in a public domain, you're assumed to be טהור. tahor.
If it's in a private domain, you're assumed to be טמא. tamei.
There are other doubts, cases of doubtful טומאה tumah and how we
deal with them based on, you know, somewhat relative arbitrary circumstances. So
this here is one of those very bizarre or very sort of,
you know, seemingly arbitrary rules. And it says, if I were to
touch this thing, decomposed thing, and I don't know, is this a
rat or something else? And I touched it on the land, I
would be a doubtful טומאה tumah and I would be טמא tamei
if it were at least in a private domain, let's say. If
I did it in the ocean and I touched it, I would
be טהור. tahor. This is a special rule that based on the
phrase 'on the land' doesn't mean that if I definitely touch a
rat on the ocean I'm טמא, tamei, but if there's a doubt,
then we rule with doubts differently on the land than in the
ocean. Very, very strange rule. Yes.
Including
if it's alive or dead?
It's only, it only causes טומאה tumah when it's dead. It's actually
interesting that the גמרא Gemara does not spell that out too much,
especially in the case of touching an egg of a lizard where
if I touch the lizard itself I'm only טמא tamei if it's
dead, but if I touch the somehow the egg and the fetus
growing inside that causes טומאה tumah even when it's alive. But actually
the תורה Torah is quite explicit. It says אשר יפל מהם במותם
יטמא, asher yipol mehem bemotam yitma, you know, when they're dead. So
but it is true that it's not clear here. But what we
are learning out from 'on the land' is yes it causes טומאה
tumah in the sea, but if it's doubtful we're more lenient if
somehow it was floating. I assume the phrase of floating means it
didn't happen to be like you're on a boat and you touch
something which might have been a dead rat on a boat. Because
then the טומאה tumah is not, it's on the boat, it's not
in the sea itself. But somehow if it's floating in the sea,
that allows for leniency. I mean if you wanted to give a
logic you could just say the likelihood that there are a lot
of other things that are floating in the sea that might look
like טומאה, tumah, you know, also the principle of רשות הרבים Reshut
Harabim and רשות היחיד, Reshut Hayachid, you know, could very well be
that since we're, we normally are lenient with a טומאה tumah in
רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim that maybe the sea is almost you know,
what would you have, a private little ocean? But I mean one
wonders is it limited to the sea, let's say I have it,
you have a private lake and it's floating in my private lake.
So anyway it is one of those arbitrary laws about doubtful טומאה.
tumah.
And does it stay until the טבילה? Tevilah?
Yeah, although I presumably, that's a good question. How do you define
floating, right? I was assuming it has to be within a natural
body of water but I'm not, I'd have to look into that.
Yeah. Charlie you had a question? Okay so let's take a look.
So it says don't we need it to, for that case? So
the גמרא Gemara says תרי השרץ על הארץ כתיבי. Trei hasharetz al
ha'aretz ktivei. No, it says השרץ על הארץ hasharetz al ha'aretz twice.
And therefore one is to tell me only land rats and the
other is to tell me this special הלכה halacha that if it's
floating and there's a doubt about it that I can be lenient.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we are going to get to
more of these שרצים sheratzim that cause טומאה tumah and some also,
you know, some understandings that חזל Chazal had about how they were
created, at least some of them. הצב למינהו, Hatzav leminehu, the צב
tzav according to its kind. Again that's seemingly one type of a
lizard, a chameleon, something along those, those lines. So להביא, l'havi, what
does that include? הערוד. Haarod. Now the הערוד Haarod is a funny
word because it's often talks about, it often seems to be if
you the, yeah the צב tzav switches to הערפד, haarvad, not הערוד,
haarod, because the הערוד Haarod is often in some גמרות Gemaras is
like a wild donkey and that certainly would not be here in
the lizard category.
So it seems to be a similar phrase term that was used
for some kind of a, you know, of a reptile like of
an animal, but still one that was as we'll see lethal.
Remember the story in the גמרא Gemara about who was it who
was דאוונינג davening by the hole and this ערוד arod came out
and bit him and it died because he was in middle of
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and he didn't interrupt? And he said this
teaches you that it's not the ערוד arod that kills but it's
the sin that kills? Since he was, you know, דאוונינג davening and
he was so holy it did not have an effect on him.
That was in the middle of גמרא ברכות Gemara Brachos that talks
about the importance of not interrupting your דאוונינג. davening. Okay so anyway
so let's take a look.
Oh yeah, רבי חנינא בן דוסא. Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa. He was
the one that he that it bit him and the ארפד arvad
or the ערוד arod died. וכן הנפילים, V'chen hanifilim, included in this
צב tzav are something called נפילים, nifilim, some have the גירסא girsa
ובן הנפילים, uven hanifilim, whatever that means, a certain type of again
lizard. הסלמנדרא. Hasalamandra. Now there we know what that means, a salamander.
Okay. ובשעה Ubshaeh רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva מגיע לפסוק זה, megia lapasuk zeh, when he reached
this verse of הצב למינהו Hatzav leminehu and he said, you know,
and it included all these things and we'll see the גמרא Gemara
believed that a salamander had like magical qualities and that was included
in this verse, היה אומר, haya omer, so what would he say?
אומר מה רבו מעשיך השם. Omer mah rabu maasecha Hashem. Oh God
how great are your creations. He used this as an opportunity to
reflect on, you know, the beauty of the diversity of creation and
all of these animals which were included in this צב. tzav. יש
לך בריות גדולות בים ויש לך בריות גדולות ביבשה. Yesh lecha briyot
gedolot bayam v'yesh lecha briyot gedolot bayabasha. You have tremendous creatures in
the ocean. Tremendous creatures on the land. שבים אלמלא עולות ביבשה מיד
מתות. Shebayam ilmale olot bayabasha miyad metot. If one of the sea
ones was on the land, let's say a whale came onto the
land, it would die. So it's, it might be a mighty creature,
a shark, a whale in the ocean, but it could only be
in the ocean.
שבייבשה, Shebayabasha, a land animal, you take I don't know, an elephant,
a lion, אלמלא יורדות לים, Ilmale yordot layam, you put them in
the ocean, מיד מתות, miyad metot, they would immediately die. יש לך
בריות גדולות באור ויש לך בריות גדולות באוויר. Yesh lecha beriyot gedolot
ba'or veyesh lecha beriyot gedolot ba'avir. You have great fire creatures and
great air creatures. Air creatures are obviously the birds. שבבאור אלמלא עולות
לאוויר, Sheba'or ilmale olot la'avir, if the fire creatures would be in
the air, we'll talk about what those fire creatures are in a
minute, they would immediately מיד מתות, miyad metot, they die immediately. שבבאוויר
אלמלא יורדות לאור, Sheba'avir ilmale yordot la'or, if you had an air
creature that went into the fire, מיד מתות, miyad metot, it would
immediately die. מה רבו מעשיך ה', Ma rabu ma'asecha Hashem, how great
are Your creations, meaning it's the diversity but also the almost, you
know, the way in which they're particularly suited for their environment. And
the amphibians, that's a good point. Right. It is interesting that the
greatness is the fact that they somehow work distinctively within their environment,
right? It's not, you know, you might say it's great that it
could live in any environment, but somehow it's almost like it's almost
like
the adaptability, the way you've made, you know, the world so that
everything fits its place and is adaptable in its place and is
made specifically to work with its function seems to be the point.
But anyway, the fire ones is the salamander. They believe that a
salamander was created from fire, or at least I don't know, lived
in fire, I think created from fire, and that if you used
the blood of the salamander and you anointed yourself with it, that
you would be fireproof. So that was the salamander that was believed
to be this like fire creature. Okay. Why are salamanders red?
What? Are they different colors?
Yellow, red.
Rashi says it's created from fire and from myrtle branches through magic,
okay, but they believe that it would give you
fireproofing qualities.
Not reproducing ordinary...
Right. Was Rabbi Akiva the one that said, who was the one
that had the, that said, you know, when he was asked why
are you learning Torah and the Romans wondered and he said it's
like the fish that if it leaves the water it will immediately
die? Was that Rabbi Akiva? Yeah, so here he is talking about,
you know, the sea creatures that if they go onto land they'll
immediately die. Okay, so anyway, alright. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our Rabbis
taught. כל שיש ביבשה יש בים חוץ מן החולדה. Kol sheyesh bayabasha
yesh bayam chutz min hachulda. Every animal, or at least it means
maybe the שרצים sheratzim that are mentioned in the list, there's some
parallel in the ocean, maybe something called by the same name. We
already saw that before by the עכבר, achbar, there was a sea
עכבר, achbar, with the exception of the חולדה. chulda. אמר רבי זירא,
Amar Rabbi Zeira, מאי קרא, mai kra, where do you get that
from the verse? האזינו כל יושבי חלד, Ha'azinu kol yoshvei chaled, listen
all people that dwell on the land. So חלד chaled is a
word that means dry land, but here it's saying that it's used
the word חלד chaled from חולדה chulda because חולדה chulda is the
type of animal that only exists as a land animal. So that's
referred to shows that that's the phrase חלד chaled is somehow means
land. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei deRav
Yehoshua, ביברי דנרש אינם מן היישוב. Bivrei deNarsh einam min hayishuv. These
people that live, Rashi says the word ביברי דנרש Bivrei deNarsh means
wild animals of this place Narsh, are not from the יישוב yishuv
could mean like settled society. But Rashi says this means that these
animals in Narsh are only sea animals, they don't have really so
many land animals. תוספות Tosafot says that doesn't really fit in the
next line that the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So תוספות
Tosafot actually understands it means no, the people of this place of
Narsh are really not מן היישוב min hayishuv means like are not
from culture, society, or, civilized, thank you, that was the word I
was looking for, are not civilized. And this is going to lead
to a whole discussion about evil people that live in Narsh and
evil people that live elsewhere. So the people from this place are
not from civilized society. Yes.
I just found a translation, bevaray as beavers.
Oh that's quite interesting. So that suggests for once I actually give
translate a type of an animal, right? That's Rashi I think just
translated it as generically meaning animals. I think we had the word
ביברי bevaray before which just meant animals. But anyway, that's interesting. Okay.
תוספות Tosafot says that it means the people from this place are
not civilized. That's what אינם מן היישוב einam min hayishuv is. It
fits with the continued context so we'll read it תוספות'ס Tosafot's way.
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, so you'll see how it fits
with the next line, said Rav Papa, בשמתא נרש טרבי משכי ואליפתא.
Beshamta Narsh tarbei mashchei ve'alifta. So let there be under the
ban like in חרם, cherem, the people of Narsh, the fat, the
skin, and the fat tail, meaning all of them, every single one
of them is wicked, they should all be under the ban. This
is a city filled with wicked people, which fits with if the
before was saying that they're not civilized. And now we're going to
go on with that theme. ארץ ארץ ארץ שמעי דבר ה', Eretz
eretz eretz shimi devar Hashem, land land land hear the word of
God. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, so Rav Papa interpreted this
to be referring to the people of Narsh. לא אבא נרש שמוע
דבר ה', Lo ava Narsh shemo'a devar Hashem, it's like the נביא
navi is calling out. to the people of נרש *Narsh* and they
refuse to listen to the word of God. They're just so wicked.
אמר רב גידל אמר רב *Amar Rav Gidal Amar Rav* נרשאה נשקיך
נשקיך *Narshaa nashkeikh nashkeikh*
if a person from נרשאה *Narshaa* kisses you, מני ככיך *mani kicheich*
count your teeth. So, all right. Now, while we're on that topic,
נהר פקודא לויך *Nahar Pekuda lavyach* if somebody from this place נהר
פקודא *Nahar Pekoda* accompanies you, מגלימא שפירא דחזי לך *miglima shapira dechazei
lach* it's because he sees you're wearing a nice cloak. So be
careful, you know, what he's, you know, watch your possessions.
I
know, right, about וישקהו *vayishakeihu*, וישקהו מפינטל״ך *vayishakeihu midpintelach*. So, okay. Where
were we? פומבדיתא לויך *Pumbedita lavyach* if a person from פומבדיתא *Pumbedita*
accompanies you, אשני אושפיזך *ashneih ushpizach* it would be to change your
address, change your inn because he's trying to find out where you're
staying so he can come at night and rob you. Now again,
one wonders were they referring to the Jews that lived, I mean,
you had a great ישיבה *yeshiva* in פומבדיתא *Pumbedita*. Yeah. Are they
referring to the non-rabbinic classes? Are they referring to the non-Jews? But
at least they were, you know, saying, they were being somewhat critical
or descriptive of certain locales about, you know, protect yourself.
Is that the source of the term נארישקייט *narshkeit*? That's a good
question.
No, that comes from נער *naar*. נער *naar* like youth, you know,
like, like, you know, childishness. Childishness is נארישקייט *narshkeit*. Yeah. Okay. So,
אמר רב הונא בר תורתא *Amar Rav Huna bar Turta*. So רב
הונא בר תורתא *Rav Huna bar Turta* said, פעם אחת הייתי לועד
*paam achas hayisi l'vad* once I went to some type of a
convocation or רש״י *Rashi* says it specifically means a gathering where people
were doing this, we'll see, cross-breeding. וראיתי נחש *V'raisi nachash* now we're
going to be back to some of these animals, I saw a
snake שהוא כרוך על הצב *sheu karuch al hatzav* which was entwined
with the צב *tzav* some type of a lizard. And they were
mating. לימים יצא ערוד מביניהם *L'yamim yatza arod mibeineihem* and then this
ערוד *arod* this other type of presumably not wild donkey but other
type of thing called an ערוד *arad* which is some type of
a lethal lizard, lethal snake, emerged from them, was the, you know,
was produced from this cross-breeding. וכשבאתי לפני רבי שמעון החסיד אמר לי
*Uchshebati lifnei Rabi Shimon HaChasid amar lei* when I came to רבי
שמעון החסיד *Rabi Shimon HaChasid* interesting רבי שמעון החסיד *Rabi Shimon HaChasid*,
we don't normally hear of, you know, that person, of that תנא
*Tanna*. Anyway, אמר לי *amar lei* he said to me, אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא *amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu* הם הביאו בריה שלא בראתי בעולמי
*heim heiviu birya shelo barasi b'olami* very fitting in with פרשת נח
*Parshas Noach* and חז״ל׳ס *Chazal's* understanding about how the animals sensed, they,
these people tried to create a creature that was not part of
my natural world, they tried to create this new creature, this cross-breeding.
אף אני אביא עליהם בריה שלא בראתי בעולמי *Af ani avia aleihem
birya shelo barasi b'olami* so I will create a creature that I
had not created, meaning I will bring this ערוד *arvad* which is
this lethal and dangerous creature. So they're trying to produce something new,
fine, I'll let something new be created, but it's going to be
destructive. והאמר מר *V'hamar mar* so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
how could they even have done that? Don't we say, כל שאין
תשמישן ועיבורן שוה אין יולדין זה מזה *kol she'ein tashmishan v'iburatan shaveh
ein yoldin zeh mizeh*? Any animals that have sex in the same
way, copulate in the same way, either front-to-front or front-to-back, and also
have the same gestation period, they can cross-breed. וכל שאין תשמישן ועיבורן
שוה אין יולדין ומגדלין זה מזה *V'kol she'ein tashmishan v'iburatan shaveh ein
yoldin umigadlin zeh mizeh*. But if they do not have sex the
same way or they do not have the same gestation period, then
they cannot become, they cannot cross-breed and they won't be able to
also nurse one another's young. So and obviously a snake and this
lizard have very different gestation periods. אמר רב נס בתוך נס *Amar
Rav nes b'toch nes*. It was a double miracle. Number one, that
a new creature came out. And number two, that it was able
to create a creature altogether, even though these animals cannot naturally cross-breed.
והגמרא *V'hagimara* says, הא פורענותא היא מאי נס *ha puranusa hu mai
nes*? So, that's what do you mean a miracle? This is a
negative thing, this is something dangerous that's now emerged from it. הגמרא
*The Gemara* says, no, מאי נס בתוך נס לפורענותא *mai nes b'toch
nes l'puranusa*. Yes, it's a miracle for the bad. It's a miracle
inside of a miracle that is a punishment to people for having
created this. So actually, this is quite fascinating, you know, in terms
of contemporary questions about genetic engineering, right? Because there's really like, you
know, there's, I mean, it's actually quite fascinating, you know, there are
פסוקים pesukim *psukim* against cross-breeding animals, right? There are פסוקים pesukim *psukim*
against, you know, there's biblical prohibitions cross-breeding animals, cross-breeding seeds, there's even
the mixing of flax and linen together and so on. You know,
so, but there's nothing that prohibits, you know, certain types of, I'm
sorry, I meant linen and wool, wool and linen, thank you. But
there's nothing that prohibits, you know, in the תורה Torah *Torah*, what
do you call it, you know, genetic engineering or cloning, all the
new science. You know, do you try to sort of say that,
you know, well, the implicit values here is about, you know, not
doing these types of new things, and that should somehow guide, or
is it only because of the biblical verse, and if this isn't
biblically prohibited, so you know, the language here, they're trying to create
something new that I haven't created in my world seems to be
in- indicating like
this value of not trying to do these new creatures now,
at least in terms of the animal world. It's not like we're
not supposed to create new things. That's the opening verses of the
תורה. Torah וכבשוה ורדו בדגת הים, v'chivshuha u'redu b'digat hayam, human innovation,
but the other opening verses in the תורה Torah are
למינהו ולמינהו ולמינהו, l'minehu u'l'minehu u'l'minehu, that at least with the natural
creatures and the plants and whatever, keeping things within their right species.
But one wonders, again, let's say something new that isn't coming through
crossing species, cloning, it's not coming through crossing species. Is that fundamentally
problematic or not? So these are interesting areas in which there are
not clear הלכות halachos about them, and how much do you allow
yourself to be guided by what might be the values of the
פסוקים pesukim when those things are not black and white. Okay, so
I wasn't expecting that in the middle of a whole discussion about,
see, this is what keeps you learning this פרק perek which is
all about the skin and the meat is that if you keep
at it long enough, you're going to find a גמרא Gemara like
this. Okay. השם Hashem as well has said
God created different species with the capacity to reproduce with each other,
like a donkey and a mule. Right, so this is God created
them, permitting them to reproduce something else.
Right,
so it is true, meaning while on the one hand we're not
allowed to crossbreed, we can certainly benefit, and mules are critical, were
a critical part of
civilization. And they were good.
Right,
right, and I mean, but at least the act is still prohibited
of crossbreeding animals. But yes, that's why
the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet here tries to deal with this a
little
bit. Yeah,
he tries to read the גמרא Gemara a little bit differently and
saying that once people started trying to crossbreed, God made it that
sometimes these things would like that there would be a potential for
these things to produce dangerous outcomes, which in a way, if you
read it that way, maybe means speaks more towards human responsibility, that
if we're trying to create something new that God hasn't created, we
have to realize that we have
potential for good but also potential for tremendous potential for
bad. So anyway, the way he reads it is slightly differently. He
says it's not talking about this particular act. He says from the
time that crossbreeding began in the world, he actually refers to the
פסוקים in the תורה Torah which are understood to refer to the
donkeys, to the mules, excuse me, הוא מצא את הימם במדבר. hu
matza et hayeimim bamidbar. So one understanding is that that refers to
having crossbred a horse and a donkey and making a mule. He
says that God said from the time humans began crossbreeding, I decreed
that this act of crossbreeding could produce potential dangerous things, potential dangerous
animals. So read that
way, the point is it speaks, I think, towards the power that
human beings can unleash, like when you find nuclear energy, could be
tremendous good, could be tremendous evil, and the question is it speaks
to the enormity of the human responsibility if it has the potential
of being bad, but not that it necessarily is bad. So I
think that's a slightly different way of reading it. Yes.
It's not clear from the words of the תורה Torah,
exactly what constitutes, what are two species? Right, that is true too.
There
are dogs that look very, very different. Right, right.
So that's why there's a whole מסכת כלאים Masechet Kilayim to try
to define what are different species of animals. Never mind that. Yes,
well it's in זרעים Zeraim and there's no גמרא Gemara on it.
Yes. Just a nice סברא sevara that occurred to me. It seems
to me that it emphasizes that השם Hashem is the creator and
that השם Hashem has created a world, he's created animals, created seeds
and plants and
whatever, and that that's the definitive statement of the world. And that
once we get into
crossbreeding, you say there could be danger. The point is a lot
of times we cannot even anticipate what that danger can be as
much as we may want to be responsible.
Right, right, I think you're right. I mean look, there are most
of the things that are basically we just read the פסוקים in
בראשית Bereishit and it's, the plants are created למינהו, l'minehu, the animals
are created למינהו, l'minehu, and there are later in the תורה Torah
explicit prohibitions of crossing species of animals and crossing species of plants.
So yes, I mean the
תורה, Rivka's question is a good one that sometimes it leads to
good and society would have been a lot harder for society to
progress in certain ways without mules. Mules were very critical in whatever.
And at the same time, the תורה prohibits doing it. It doesn't
always prohibit the result of it. So I think you are right
that the and which is the general sense of this גמרא Gemara.
is you're playing with fire and therefore don't play with it. Yes,
sometimes it can be constructive, but don't play with it. That seems
to be the message. It does raise very interesting questions, as I
said, about things that are not explicitly prohibited, like contemporary issues about
genetic engineering and so on.
Would they have said that people of different races should not interbreed?
I don't think so. I don't think you ever get that. You
never get the למינהו leminehu by humans, you never get biblical issues.
I think this is very consistent with the descriptions in בראשית Bereishit
and the later prohibitions, which are specifically למינהו leminehu by plants and
למינהו leminehu by animals. Yeah. By the way, the כלאים, kilayim, I
mean, I forgot who I first saw this from, and then we
have to go on, but I think it was Mary Douglas made
this point, I could never understand like the wool and the linen,
what's the problem with that? And she makes the point that wool
is from the animal kingdom and linen is from the plant kingdom.
So you're crossing across those lines of the plant and the animal
distinctions, you know, so those are really where those aspects of כלאים
kilayim come from. Alright, let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishna. העבר והבשר המדולדלים בבהמה ha'eiver vehabasar hameduldalim biveheima מטמאין טומאת
אוכלין במקומן. metam'in tumat ochlin bimkoman. Now this actually we had this
concept before, if you'll remember. You have a dangling limb from a
cow, okay, or you have dangling meat, and it's still barely connected.
So what is its status before you שחט shacht the cow? So
מטמאין טומאת אוכלין במקומן. metam'in tumat ochlin bimkoman. Even while it's still
dangling and the cow isn't שחט, shachted, if the cow dies, it's
a נבלה. neveila. We'll talk about their status in a minute. But
while the cow's alive, remember we had this possibility before that you
could have something, remember when we שחט shachted the pig and it
was thrashing around and it wasn't yet a נבלה neveila but it
was food, something in a middle status? So for an inter- for
whatever reason, we have the same idea here. Dangling limb, dangling meat,
I guess in theory it's so easy to grab it off and
eat it, somehow it has a status of food, although interestingly, who
could eat it? It's not כשר kosher for a Jew, it's not
כשר kosher for a בן נח ben Noach to eat, it's אבר
מן החי, eiver min hachai, בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. But
somehow because it's like so easily to become food, it already can
be- becomes טמא. tamei. Even if the animal dies, there'd be maybe
a נבלה neveila question, but right now it's not dead. וצריכין הכשר.
u'tzrichin hechshier. It requires הכשר, hechshier, contact with a liquid, right, in
order to make all food and meat, etc., only becomes טמא, tamei,
can become טמא tamei once it's been in contact with a
liquid. Now נשחטה הבהמה הוכשרו בדמיה. nishcheta habeheima huchshiru bedameha. The animal
was שחט, shachted, now this meat, so it becomes- like the same
way when you שחט shacht an animal, the meat does not have
to come in contact with liquid, if you remember there was a
משנה Mishna earlier that said the act of שחיטה, shechita, not the
blood of שחיטה, shechita, the act of שחיטה shechita serves like הכשר
hechshier because it makes the animal like meat and food, you don't
need liquid. So that is true about this dangling thing as well.
Now you might also remember that even when you שחט shacht the
animal, you're not allowed to eat the dangling limb, that was learned
from a verse, some said that verse was only rabbinic, but even
though you're not allowed to eat the dangling limb, it is edible,
and because the שחיטה shechita makes the meat of the animal susceptible
and counts as הכשר, hechshier, the same is true also for this
dangling limb. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says. רבי שמעון אומר לא הוכשרו. Rabbi Shimon omer lo
huchshiru. No, the שחיטה shechita does not apply to this dangling limb.
If you can't eat the dangling limb, then the שחיטה shechita does
not make it susceptible and it would still need to come in
contact with liquid. Now that's if you שחט shacht it. What about
מתה הבהמה? meta habeheima? The animal died. What's the status about this
meat that had been dangling from it? הבשר צריך הכשר. habasar tzarich
hechshier. The meat requires הכשר. hechshier. This is interesting. It would die,
the main animal is a נבלה, neveila, you would think that this
dangling limb is also in נבלה, neveila, but no, because it was
dangling and it wasn't fully
attached, it's in a very interesting middle status. It's not detached enough
to be at this stage אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai causes its own טומאה. tumah. When the
animal's alive, it's not its own thing, it's not אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai. But as soon as the animal dies, then it
is considered to be detached from the animal. The animal is a
נבלה, neveila, this limb is not, and this limb, if it comes
in contact with liquid, only then will it be susceptible to
טומאה. tumah. Okay. האבר מטמא משום אבר מן החי ואינו מטמא משום
אבר נבלה דברי רבי מאיר ורבי שמעון מטהר. ha'eiver metamei mishum eiver
min hachai ve'eino metamei mishum eiver neveila divrei Rabbi Meir veRabbi Shimon
metaher. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir actually qualifies, and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says the following, and he's- he says look, the- that is
the meat. The meat that's dangling when the animal dies, even if
it were בשר מן החי, basar min hachai, בשר מן החי basar
min hachai does not cause טומאה. tumah. The basic difference between בשר
מן החי basar min hachai and אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai,
just the flesh or a whole limb, they're both forbidden to eat
even for בני נח, bnei Noach, the difference is that the flesh
does not cause טומאה, tumah, the אבר eiver does. So he says
like this, he says if the animal dies, the flesh, if it's
just dangling flesh, so I don't care if I call that בשר
מן החי basar min hachai or not, it's not going to cause
טומאה, tumah, okay, but- and he actually says it's not part of
the נבלה. neveila. So it's not part of the נבלה, neveila, it's
not בשר מן החי, basar min hachai, so therefore it's just meat,
so you have to come- it comes in contact with a liquid.
That's about the meat. But the dangling limb, that he says is
not part of the נבלה. neveila. How do we say that it's
not part of the נבלה? neveila? We have to imagine that when
the animal died, it's like the meat and like the limb fell
off. That would be the only way we would call it not
part of the animal, not to be a נבלה. neveila. Well, if
they fell off while the animal is dying, then it's בשר מן
החי basar min hachai or אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. So
therefore the limb is a problem of אבר מן החי, eiver min
hachai, not נבלה, neveila, but אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. So
again, it's a little confusing, maybe I didn't explain it so well,
so I'll try again to be clear. So here you have this
dangling limb. While the animal's alive... It's not נבלה, nevela, it's not
whatever, it's not אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, it's not, it's
still connected. What it is is it can become טמא tamei like
food. Once the animal's שחט, shechted, then it's שחט, shechted, it's also
out of the category of being a problem. But if the animal
dies, the animal becomes a נבלה. nevela. And the process of the
animal dying and becoming a נבלה, nevela, we're saying these dangling things
are not a נבלה nevela with the animal. If they're not a
נבלה nevela with the animal, how do we conceptually explain that? It's
as if they fell off. Oh, they fell off, so what's their
status if they fell off? Well, if the meat fell off, it's
בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. בשר מן החי basar min hachai
doesn't cause טומאה. tuma. Meat that fell off in the animal's life
doesn't cause טומאה tuma until it has to come in contact with
liquid. If a limb fell off, it's אבר מן החי eiver min
hachai and that does cause טומאה. tuma. So that's the first opinion.
האבר מטמא משום אבר מן החי ואינו מטמא משום אבר נבלה. ha'eiver
metamei mishum eiver min hachai ve'eino metamei mishum eiver nevela. It's considered
like it fell off, so it's considered as an אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, not the אבר, eiver, not the limb of a
נבלה. nevela. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what Meir says.
רבי שמעון מטהר, Rabbi Shimon metaher, Rabbi Shimon says it's totally טהור.
tahor. It's neither one or the other. It's not a נבלה, nevela,
it's not אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. So we'll have to
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look in
the גמרא. Gemara טומאת אוכלין איכא טומאת נבלה ליכא. tumat ochlin ika
tumat nevela leika. So this dangling limb or dangling meat causes טומאה
tuma of a, of, of food, but not the טומאה tuma of
נבלה. nevela. Okay, meaning, now the גמרא Gemara, really doesn't mean נבלה.
nevela. If you look at the little תוספות Tosafot here, טומאת נבלה
דמשתעי כאן ש"ס לאו דווקא והיינו טומאת אבר מן החי. tumat nevela
demishtaei kan Shas lav davka vehaynu tumat eiver min hachai. Okay, it's
not טומאת נבלה. tumat nevela. Obviously the animal's alive. So what it
means is you've got this dangling limb and we say while the
animal is living, we say it's like food, it's detached enough that
we'll consider it like food and it can become טומאת tumat food,
but it's not fully detached to be considered an אבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, a limb from a live animal that causes
טומאה. tuma. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דמלינא ארוכה,
ei demalina arucha, if
it could heal itself, if this dangling thing can
heal, אפילו טומאת אוכלין נמי לא תטמא, afilu tumat ochlin nami lo
titamei, don't consider it food, it's going to heal, it's going to
become, you know, reintegrated into the animal. ואי דאין מלינא ארוכה, ve'ei
de'ein malina arucha, if it cannot heal, טומאת נבלה נמי תטמא, tumat
nevela nami titamei,
so consider it to be fully detached and consider it to be,
again, not נבלה nevela but אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. Okay,
what is this middle status of a dangling limb that's detached enough
to be considered food, not part of the animal, but not detached
enough that it's not
אבר מן החי? eiver min hachai? לעולם דאין מלינא ארוכה, le'olam de'ein
malina arucha, it's not going to heal. ושאני טומאת נבלה, veshani tumat
nevela, again meaning אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, רחמנא אמר כי
יפול, Rachmana amar ki yipol, when it falls, these things fall, עד
שיפול. ad sheyipol. Something will only be a נבלה nevela when it
actually dies or will only be אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
when the limb actually falls off. So it's detached enough to be
considered not part of the animal enough so that it's in this
gray zone, meaning basically the גמרא, Gemara you know, does this, sort
of is fascinated by this at various times, something that's neither one
nor the other. It's neither part of the animal, but it's not
yet removed from the animal. So if it's not part of the
animal, it could be טמא tamei as food, but it's not yet
detached from the animal, so it's not yet an אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai. אבר מן החי eiver min hachai is only when
something fully is detached. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, האבר והבשר המדולדלין בבהמה, ha'eiver vehabasar hameduldalin bibehema, if you
have a limb or meat that is dangling from an
animal, ומעורין בחוט השערה, ume'urin bechut hasa'ara, still intertwined with like one
strand, meaning there's still some point of connection to the main
animal, יכול יטמאו טומאת נבלה, yachol yitame'u tumat nevela, maybe they're טמא
tamei like a נבלה, nevela, again doesn't literally mean נבלה, nevela, like
אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, maybe it's like they already fell
off, תלמוד לומר יפול עד שיפול, talmud lomar yipol ad sheyipol, until
it actually falls off. So again, an animal is not yet food,
so an animal can't be טומאת tumat food. Because this is dangling,
we envision it as like it's quasi-food already, it's dangling, it's no
longer part of this cow, but therefore it could become טמא tamei
as food, but because it hasn't actually fallen off, it's not yet
an אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. To be an אבר מן
החי, eiver min hachai, it has to fully detach itself from the
animal. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, אפילו הכי טומאת אוכלין
מטמא. afilu hachi tumat ochlin metamei.
So we're saying even though it's not yet fallen off, it still
is טמא tamei like food. מסייע ליה לרבי חייא בר אשי, mesayei
lei leRabbi Chiya bar Ashi, this supports Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi. דאמר
רבי חייא בר אשי אמר שמואל, de'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar
Shmuel, תאנים שצמקו באיביהן, te'einim shetzamku be'avihen, another type of case moving
from the animal world to the plant world where something is in
this gray zone. You have a fig that is, like, dried up
on its, you know, on its stem, on the tree. So if
the stem is dried, it's considered already fully detached. But the stem
isn't dried, but the fruit is dried. So the fruit is, it's
in this state of being like quasi-detached. So what's the status of
this middle
state? המטמא טומאת אוכלין, hametamei tumat ochlin, it's enough food, we don't
look at it as an integral part of the tree anymore, so
it could become טמא tamei as food. And at the same time,
והתולש מהם בשבת חייב חטאת, vehatolesh mehem beShabbat chayav chatat, if you
pull it off on שבת, Shabbat, you have to bring a חטאת,
chatat, a sin offering, you violated שבת Shabbat because it still is
connected to the tree. So you've got a very analogous case, right?
It's not fully detached. If it were seen as fully detached, you
wouldn't be חייב chayav for picking it on שבת. Shabbat. But it's
not fully attached, then it would not be טמא tamei as food.
It's in this middle state where it's enough independent from it that
it could be seen as food, but it's still enough connected that
it does not have that fully independent status. matter. So in one
case because it's connected, it's not טמא tamei as אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai by the limb of the animal. In the case
of the fruit from the tree, because it's still seen as connected,
if you pick it on שבת Shabbos you violate שבת. Shabbos. Yes.
Is this a spiritual, I mean is there a medical reason that
this fruit or the limb, yeah, limb or whatever it is is
not healthy?
No, it's these are very, no, no, no, these are all very
formal halachic definitions, which is how we can compare a case of
a limb to a case of fruit on a tree. These are
just questions about things that could be in this middle status and
that things when they're somehow are somewhat, you know, detached and not
fully integrated, that they could be seen as food even before they
are completely severed. So that's really the idea that this category of
טומאת אוכלים tumas ochlim can apply to something that is not fully
independent yet, but is halfway there. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesayeia lei, let me
try to give support to this idea. And now we're going to
be in the plant
world. ירקות שצימקו באיביהם. yerakot shetzimku be'iveihem. Let's say you have
vegetables that have dried up in on their, you know, on their
vine or on their, you
know, כגון, kigone, הכרוב והדלעת, hakruv vehadilaat, like
כרוב kruv דלעת dilaat is a gourd. I'm trying to remember what
a כרוב kruv is. How do they translate כרוב kruv there? It's
cabbage. Cabbage. That's what I thought. I'm not exactly sure how this
makes sense because it's going to talk about using the hardened thing
in some, well we'll take a look. Like cabbage and and I
remember once many years ago when Trivial Pursuit came out, I was
playing with this Israeli couple and the question was, what is sauerkraut?
What is sauerkraut made out of? So the husband was translating for
the wife, so he said, ממה עושים כרוב חתוך? mima osim kruv
chatuach? Because the Hebrew for sauerkraut is cut-up cabbage. So she looked
at him like, כרוב? kruv? From cabbage? So anyway, all right. So
anyway, but okay, so you have cabbage or gourd, אין מטמאין טומאת
אוכלים. ein mitamin tumas ochlim. They do not, if they're dried up,
they are not food. Now why is that different than the dried-up
fig? Because a dried-up gourd certainly, like you know, people hang this
from their סוכה, sukkah, you know, you knock them, they're hollow, you
can use them as a vessel. So a dried-up gourd is not
edible at all. Okay, so it doesn't be, it's no, if it's
really dried up, it's not food anymore. So presumably the same is
true with cabbage. So if those are dried up, they are not
food because they're no longer
edible. Now, אין מטמאין טומאת אוכלים. ein mitamin tumas ochlim. קצצן ביבשן,
katzatzan beyamshan, if however they weren't dried up, but first you cut
them when they were still moist, when they were still good, you
know, fresh and then you dried them up, מטמאין טומאת אוכלים. mitamin
tumas ochlim. Then they do become טמא tamei as food stuff, which
is interesting. Why? They're dried up now. So the גמרא Gemara says,
קצצן ביבשן סלקא דעתך? katzatzan beyamshan salka daatach? Do you literally mean
that you've dried them in the last case? עץ בעלמא הוא! etz
be'alma hu! It's like a piece of wood by the time you
dry up a gourd. I'm trying to understand cabbage. What does cabbage
look like when it's dried up?
I've never seen it.
It probably rots. But it's not like the gourd case, which is
like, gourd becomes like, yeah, like wood. Right. Anyway, okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, how could that be food if you dried it
up? דאמר רבי יצחק, de'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, בעל מנת ליבשן. be'almenas leyabshan.
It doesn't mean you literally dried it up. It means if you
cut them when they were fresh with the intention of drying, since
they're not yet dry yet, they're still considered food because now they're
still edible. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, טעמא דכרוב ודלעת. taama dekruv vedilaat. So when is
this true that when they're dried up on the vine, they're considered,
they're not food? That's about something like this, like this cabbage or
the gourd. כיון דיבשן לאו בני אכילה נינהו. keivan deyavshan lav benei
achila ninhu. Once they're dry, they're not fit to be eaten. That's
why when they dry up on the gourd, they're not food. השאר
פירות, hashar peiros, the implication is that other fruit, even if it's
dried on the gourd, on the vine, מטמאי, mitamei, are subject to
טומאה. tumah. So you see you can have something that's still on
the vine and if it doesn't become fully inedible, even if it's
dried, it's considered enough independent once it's drying out that it's enough
independent to already be food. Fruit on the tree is not yet
food, does not yet become טמא tamei as food. It has to
be picked. But here you see that if it didn't dry out,
if it dried out, it's not edible. But if it didn't dry
out, if it's still edible once it's dry, you see that it
would be considered independent enough to be food. So the
גמרא Gemara says, השאר פירות מטמאי היכי דמי? hashar peiros mitamei heichi
dami? What would be the
case? אי דיבשן הן ועוקצן, i deyavshan hen ve'uktzan, if not only
are they dry but even the twig is dry where it's connected
to the tree, פשיטא! peshita! Of course they would become, they'd be
seen as independent from the tree. In that case, if you picked
it on שבת, Shabbos, you wouldn't violate. If the twig has dried
up, then it's really seen as completely severed from the tree. You
wouldn't have to tell me that case. אלא לאו בלא עוקצן. ela
lav belo uktzan. It must mean without their twig. So it's saying
as like this, this משנה Mishnah says if you have something like
a gourd that totally dries on the vine, it's not food. The
implication is other fruit that dries on the vine is considered to
be food. Now, if it's dried up so much that even the
twig dried up, of course it has an independent status. You wouldn't
even be חייב chayiv for שבת. Shabbos. So the חידוש chiddush has
to be, the implication The wide point has to be that if
the just the fruit itself dried without the twig, it gets enough
independence to be even though for שבת Shabbos you transgress, it gets
enough independence that it's considered to be
food. So the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם הן והן, le'olam hen vehen,
let's say, really what the implication that other foods which dries up
is considered food, that it's considered fruit, it's considered food, that would
be when they dried with the twig, when it's really considered fully
severed. דכי קתני אמנסי יבש איצטריכא ליה. dechi katani amansi yavesh itztricha
lei. So why, what is the point of this משנה? Mishna? The
point of the משנה Mishna is to tell you the second case,
meaning sometimes the גמרא Gemara thinks that the whole point of a
משנה Mishna is to tell you the implied alternative. But sometimes it
says no, the point of the משנה Mishna is to tell you
the surface point that it's telling you, that when you cut it
for the intention of drying, since it's not yet dried out, this
gourd is still considered food and it still gets טומאה. tumah. So
again, the משנה Mishna said that if a gourd, if a gourd
totally dried out on the vine, it's not food. If you cut
it off the vine with the intention of drying it, it is
food. Okay? And the גמרא Gemara says, ah, that's only by a
gourd, but it seems like it's trying to tell me that if
there was something other than a gourd that dried out, that even
while it was still on the vine, it would be considered food
even though it's not, it's still connected for שבת Shabbos purposes. And
the גמרא Gemara says no, the משנה Mishna isn't bothering itself at
all with that other case. The only purpose of the משנה Mishna
is to tell you the point that when you cut this gourd
for the sake of drying, it's not the same as if it
had actually dried out. And in that case, it still is considered
food and still becomes טמא. tamei.
So we're not talking about that נפקא מינא. nafka mina.
We're not talking the right, at this stage, we're not talking about
the alternative case. We're only talking about the case in front of
us.
It becomes טמא, tamei, it becomes content.
It becomes contact, right, becomes susceptible for טומאה. tumah. תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear, אילן שנפשח, ilan shenifshach, let's say you removed
a branch from a tree that had a lot of fruit hanging
from it. Would that fruit, like you took off an apple branch
with apples connected to it, would those apples be considered susceptible for
טומאה, tumah, food? And the answer is yes, even though they're not
plucked from the branch, but the branch is just cut from the
tree. So the fruit attached to it is considered food and susceptible
for טומאה. tumah. ובו פירות, uvo peirot, and their fruit hanging from
it, הרי הן כתלושין, harei hen ketlushin, they are like they have
been plucked and they are susceptible for טומאה. tumah. יבשו, yaveshu, if
they dried out, הרי הן כמחוברין. harei hen kemechubarin. Now, meaning if
they, you did not break the branch. The branch is still connected,
but it's just the fruit has dried out, they're still then that
then they are still considered connected. So מאי לאו, mai lav, תלושין
לכל דבריהם, tlushin lechol divreihem, the same way when you break off
the branch, the fruit are considered detached for all purposes, meaning if
I broke off a branch and there are apples, those apples hanging
from the branch, number one, are food and become טמא, tamei, can
become טמא. tamei. And number two, if I pluck those apples on
שבת, Shabbos, I don't transgress because the branch is fully severed. So
the same way in the scenario of the branch when it says
they're severed, it means that they're severed for all purposes, for טומאה
tumah and for שבת Shabbos purposes. So when it says when they're
on the branch and they're dried out and they're considered connected, presumably
it means for all purposes, both for טומאה tumah and for שבת.
Shabbos. אף מחוברין לכל דבריהם. af mechubarin lechol divreihem.
Yeah, but while it's still on the tree, right.
If it's still on the tree and dried out,
so... Yes, it's no, it's not the source of טומאה, tumah, it
can, it can become טמא tamei if it comes in contact with
something טמא. tamei. Okay. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says, מידי
איריא, midi irya, is that a proof? הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא, ha
kide'ita veha kide'ita, each one is according to its own category. So
the case by the branch is a case by which it becomes
completely severed, whereas the case by the dried out fruit made it
severed for one purpose, not for the other. So again, the point
is that our משנה Mishna teaches about this dangling limb that while
the animal is alive, because it's semi-detached, you look at it as
no longer part of the animal and you look at it as
food, but because it hasn't yet been fully detached, it is not
considered to yet be אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. And the
גמרא Gemara, said there's an interesting analogy to dried out fruit on
a branch, where if it's while it's while it's completely part of
the tree, it's not food, it's not טמא. tamei. If it's dried
out and ready to fall off, so then it is considered food
and can become טמא, tamei, but because it's still connected, that connection
is meaningful that if you pluck it on שבת Shabbos you have
violated. And we tried to see if we could prove that middle
status by fruit by various משניות Mishnas and ברייתות, baraitas, and we
sort of stand with saying that that was inconclusive whether it could
be proven or not, but certainly it would be analogous to the
case, but when it is fully dried out, even the twig is
dried out, then it's considered fully severed even for שבת Shabbos purposes.
Okay, we'll end here. Yeah.
So here we have a food which is permitted eating by nobody,
but by our current understanding of the גמרא, it can still have
the טומאה tumah of food.
Food that is per... Yes, yes, that actually is quite fascinating. Yeah,
I was mentioning that, that is very bizarre that it's true, but
you are correct. Like I said, that it's not even kosher for
בני נח. bnei Noach. Right. Okay.